I thought in getting up to my TED wish
فكرت في أخذ أمنية تيد خاصتي
I would try to begin by putting in perspective what I try to do
سأحاول أن أبدأ بوضع وجهات ما أحاول فعله
and how it fits with what they try to do.
وكيف تتناسب مع ما يحاولون فعله.
We live in a world that everyone knows is interdependent,
نحن نعيش في عالم يعرف الجميع أنه مترابط،
but insufficient in three major ways.
لكنه به عجز في ثلاثة محاور رئيسية.
It is, first of all, profoundly unequal:
إنه وقبل كل شئ، غير متكافئ بشدة.
half the world's people still living on less than two dollars a day;
ما يزال نصف سكان العالم يعيشون بأقل من دولارين يومياً،
a billion people with no access to clean water;
مليار شخص لا يحصلون على مياة شرب نظيفة،
two and a half billion no access to sanitation;
أثنان مليار ونصف لا يحصلون على مرافق صحية،
a billion going to bed hungry every night;
مليار يخلدون الى النوم جوعى كل ليلة.
one in four deaths every year from AIDS, TB, malaria
واحد من كل أربعة وفيات سنوياً بسبب الإيدز، السُل، الملاريا
and the variety of infections associated with dirty water --
وتشكيلة من الإلتهابات المرتبطة بالمياة الوسخة--
80 percent of them under five years of age.
80 في المائة منهم تحت سن الخامسة.
Even in wealthy countries it is common now to see inequality growing.
حتى في البلدان الغنية من الشائع الآن أن نرى عدم المساواة يتزايد.
In the United States, since 2001 we've had five years of economic growth,
في الولايات المتحدة، منذ 2001 شهدنا خمس سنوات من النمو الإقتصادي،
five years of productivity growth in the workplace,
خمس سنوات من نمو الإنتاجية في أماكن العمل،
but median wages are stagnant and the percentage of working families
لكن متوسط الأجور في حالة ركود ونسبة الأسر العاملة
dropping below the poverty line is up by four percent.
التي تتناقص لأقل من خط الفقر أرتفعت بأربعة في المائة.
The percentage of working families without health care up by four percent.
نسبة الأسر العاملة بدون رعاية صحية أرتفع بأربعة في المائة.
So this interdependent world which has been pretty good to most of us --
إذاً هذا العالم المترابط الذي هو جيد لمعظمنا--
which is why we're all here in Northern California doing what we do
الذي يفسر لماذا نحن جميعنا في شمال كاليفورنيا نفعل ما نفعله
for a living, enjoying this evening -- is profoundly unequal.
للقمة العيش، نستمتع بهذه الأمسية-- غير متكافئ بشدة.
It is also unstable.
إنه أيضاً غير مستقر.
Unstable because of the threats of terror,
غير مستقر بسبب تهديدات الإرهاب،
weapons of mass destruction, the spread of global disease
أسلحة الدمار الشامل، إنتشار الاوبئة العالمية
and a sense that we are vulnerable to it in a way that we weren't not so many years ago.
وروح أننا ضعفاء أمامه بطريقة لم نكن عليها قبل سنوات عديدة خلت.
And perhaps most important of all, it is unsustainable
وربما الأهم من كل ذلك، أنها غير مستدامة
because of climate change, resource depletion and species destruction.
بسبب تغير المناخ، نضوب الموارد وتدمير الكائنات.
When I think about the world I would like to leave to my daughter
عندما أفكر بالعالم الذي أرغب بأن أترك لبنتي
and the grandchildren I hope to have,
وأحفادي الذين آمل أن استقبلهم،
it is a world that moves away from unequal, unstable, unsustainable
إنه العالم الذي يتحرك من غير متكافئ، غير مستقر، غير مستدام
interdependence to integrated communities -- locally, nationally and globally --
مترابط للمجتمعات المتكاملة -- محلياً، وطنياً وعالمياً--
that share the characteristics of all successful communities:
الذي يتقاسم خصائص كل المجتمعات الناجحة.
a broadly shared, accessible set of opportunities,
مجموعة فرص مشتركة على نطاق واسع،
a shared sense of responsibility for the success of the common enterprise
روح مشتركة للمسئولية من أجل نجاح المؤسسة المشتركة
and a genuine sense of belonging.
والروح الأصيلة للإنتماء.
All easier said than done.
جميعها سهل قولها اكتر من فعلها.
When the terrorist incidents occurred in the United Kingdom a couple of years ago,
عندما ظهرت الحوادث الإرهابية في المملكة المتحدة قبل عدة سنوات مضت،
I think even though they didn't claim as many lives as we lost in the United States on 9/11,
أعتقد أنه رغماً عن أنها لم توقع خسائر في الأرواح مثلما حدث في الولايات المتحدة في 9/11,
I think the thing that troubled the British most
أعتقد أن الشئ الذي أزعج الإنجليز أكثر
was that the perpetrators were not invaders, but homegrown citizens
كان أن الجناة لم يكونو غزاة، لكنهم مواطنين محليين
whose religious and political identities were more important to them
الذين كانت هوياتهم الدينية والسياسية أكثر أهمية بالنسبة لهم
than the people they grew up with, went to school with,
عن الناس الذين نشأوا معهم، ذهبوا معهم الى المدارس،
worked with, shared weekends with, shared meals with.
عملوا معهم، تقاسموا أواخر الأسبوع معهم، والأكل معهم.
In other words, they thought their differences
بكلمات أخرى، لقد أعتقدوا أن إختلافاتهم
were more important than their common humanity.
ستكون أكثر أهمية من إنسانيتهم المشتركة.
It is the central psychological plague of humankind in the 21st century.
هذا هو الطاعون وسط النفسية للبشرية في القرن الحادي والعشرين.
Into this mix, people like us, who are not in public office,
في هذا الخليط، الناس من أمثالنا الذين ليسوا في مناصب عامة،
have more power to do good than at any time in history,
لديهم قوة أكثر لفعل الخير عن أي وقت في التاريخ،
because more than half the world's people
لأن أكثر من نصف سكان العالم
live under governments they voted in and can vote out.
يعيشون تحت حكومات صوتوا لها ويمكن التصويت عليها.
And even non-democratic governments are more sensitive to public opinion.
وحتى الحكومات غير الديموقراطية أكثر حساسية تجاه الرأي العام.
Because primarily of the power of the Internet,
لسبب أساسي هو قوة الإنترنت،
people of modest means can band together and amass vast sums of money
ويمكن للناس بوسائل متواضعة التجمع سوياً وجمع مبالغة طائلة من المال
that can change the world for some public good if they all agree.
الذي يستطيع تغيير العالم لبعض الخير الذي يتفق عليه الجميع.
When the tsunami hit South Asia, the United States contributed 1.2 billion dollars.
عندما ضرب التسونامي جنوب آسيا، ساهمت الولايات المتحدة ب 1.2 مليار دولار.
30 percent of our households gave.
30 في المائة من أسرنا ساهموا.
Half of them gave over the Internet.
نصفهم ساهم عبر الإنترنت.
The median contribution was somewhere around 57 dollars.
متوسط المساهمات كان حوالي 57 دولاراً.
And thirdly, because of the rise of non-governmental organizations.
وثالثاً، بسبب ظهور المنظمات غير الحكومية.
They, businesses, other citizens' groups, have enormous power
فالأعمال، والمجموعات المدنية الأخرى، لديهم قوة هائلة
to affect the lives of our fellow human beings.
في التأثير على حياة أخوانهم في الإنسانية.
When I became president in 1993,
عندما أصبحت رئيساً عام 1993،
there were none of these organizations in Russia.
لم تكن هناك أي من هذه المنظمات في روسيا.
There are now a couple of hundred thousand.
هناك الآن مئات الآلاف منها.
None in India. There are now at least a half a million active.
لا توجد في الهند. هناك الآن على الأقل نصف مليون منظمة ناشطة.
None in China. There are now 250,000 registered with the government,
لا توجد في الصين. هناك الآن 250 ألف مسجلة مع الحكومة،
probably twice again that many who are not registered for political reasons.
على الأرجح ضعف ذلك الكثير غير المسجل بسبب أسباب سياسية.
When I organized my foundation, and I thought about the world as it is
عندما نظمت مؤسستي، وفكرت في العالم كما هو
and the world that I hope to leave to the next generation,
والعالم الذي آمل أن أتركه للجيل القادم،
and I tried to be realistic about what I had cared about all my life
وحاولت أن أكون واقعياً حول ما أهتميت به طوال حياتي
that I could still have an impact on.
والذي ما يزال لدي تأثير عليه.
I wanted to focus on activities
أردت التركيز على أنشطة
that would help to alleviate poverty, fight disease, combat climate change,
ستساعد في التخفيف من الفقر، تكافح الأمراض، تكافح تغير المناخ،
bridge the religious, racial and other divides that torment the world,
تقلل الفوارق الدينية، العرقية وبقية الفوارق التي تعذب العالم،
but to do it in a way that would either use
لكن لفعلها بطريقة أسهل في الإستخدام
whatever particular skills we could put together in our group
غض النظر عن المهارات المحددة التي يمكن وضعها سوياً في مجموعتنا
to change the way some public good function was performed
لتغيير الطريقة التي عُملت بها بعض الأشياء الجيدة
so that it would sweep across the world more.
بحيث تنتشر في أنحاء العالم أكثر.
You saw one reference to that in what we were able to do with AIDS drugs.
لقد رأيتم مرجع واحد لذلك في ما أستطعنا فعله مع دواء الإيدز.
And I want to say that the head of our AIDS effort,
وأرغب في القول أن قائد جهودنا تجاه الإيدز،
and the person who also is primarily active in the wish I'll make tonight,
والشخص الناشط في الأساس في الأمنية التي سأتمناها الليلة،
Ira Magaziner, is here with me and I want to thank him for everything he's done.
آرا ماغانيزنر، هنا معي وأرغب في شكره على كل شئ فعله.
He's over there.
إنه هناك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
When I got out of office and was asked to work, first in the Caribbean,
عندما خرجت من المنصب وطُلب مني العمل، بداية في الكاربيين،
to try to help deal with the AIDS crisis,
أو محاولة المساعدة في التعامل مع أزمة الإيدز،
generic drugs were available for about 500 dollars a person a year.
كانت العقاقير المتوفرة بحوالي 500 دولار للشخص سنوياً.
If you bought them in vast bulks,
إذا أشتريتهم بالجملة،
you could get them at a little under 400 dollars.
يمكنك الحصول عليها بأقل قليل من 400 دولار.
The first country we went to work in, the Bahamas,
أول دولة ذهبنا للعمل فيها، البهاما،
was paying 3,500 dollars for these drugs.
كانت تدفع 3500 دولار لتلك العقاقير.
The market was so terribly disorganized
كانت السوق غير منظم على نحو مؤلم
that they were buying this medicine through two agents
بحيث أنهم يشترون هذه الأدوية عبر وسيطين
who were gigging them sevenfold.
الذين يعزفون عليهم سبع مرات.
So the very first week we were working,
إذاً في الأسبوع الأول الذي عملنا فيه،
we got the price down to 500 dollars.
خفّضنا السعر الى 500 دولار.
And all of a sudden, they could save seven times as many lives
وفجأة، أمكنهم الحفاظ على حياة سبعة
for the same amount of money.
أشخاص بنفس مبلغ المال.
Then we went to work with the manufacturers of AIDS medicines,
ثم ذهبنا للعمل مع مصنعي أدوية الإيدز،
one of whom was cited in the film,
أحدهم تم ذكره في الفيلم،
and negotiated a whole different change in business strategy,
وفاوضنا على تغيير كامل في إستراتيجية العمل.
because even at 500 dollars, these drugs
لأنه حتى بسعر 500 دولار، هذه الأدوية
were being sold on a high-margin, low-volume, uncertain-payment basis.
كانت تُباع بربح بسيط، كميات صغيرة، أساس دفع غير مضمون.
So we worked on improving the productivity of the operations
لذا فقد عملنا على تحسين الإنتاجية في العمليات
and the supply chain, and went to a low-margin, high-volume,
وسلسلة التوريد، وأصبحنا بهامش بسيط، كميات كبيرة،
absolutely certain-payment business.
ووعمل دفعيات مؤكدة تماماً.
I joked that the main contribution we made
كنت أمزح بأن مساهمتنا الرئيسية التي أنجزناها
to the battle against AIDS was to get the manufacturers
في مجال مكافحة الإيدز كانت جعل المصنعين
to change from a jewelry store to a grocery store strategy.
يغيرون من إستراتيجية متجر الجواهر الى متجر الخضار.
But the price went to 140 dollars from 500.
لكن السعر أنخفض الى 140 دولار من 500.
And pretty soon, the average price was 192 dollars.
وفي القريب ، كان متوسط السعر 192 دولاراً.
Now we can get it for about 100 dollars.
الآن يمكن أن نحصل عليه بحوالي 100 دولار.
Children's medicine was 600 dollars,
دواء الأطفال كان ب 600 دولار،
because nobody could afford to buy any of it.
لأنه لا أحد كان بمقدوره شراء أي منه.
We negotiated it down to 190.
قمنا بالتفاوض بتخيفضه ل 190.
Then, the French imposed their brilliantly conceived airline tax
ثم، فرض الفرنسيون ببراعتهم ضرائب خطوط الطيران
to create a something called UNITAID,
لإقامة شئ يسمى يونايتدايد (UNITAID)
got a bunch of other countries to help.
وحصلوا على بضع دول أخرى للمساعدة.
That children's medicine is now 60 dollars a person a year.
دواء الأطفال الآن ب 60 دولاراً للفرد في السنة.
The only thing that is keeping us from basically saving the lives
الشئ والوحيد الذي يمنعنا من الحفاظ على أرواح
of everybody who needs the medicine to stay alive
الذين يحتاجون للدواء للبقاء على قيد الحياة
are the absence of systems necessary to diagnose, treat and care
هو غياب الأنظمة الضرورية للتشخيص، العلاج والرعاية
for people and deliver this medicine.
للناس وإرسال هذا الدواء.
We started a childhood obesity initiative with the Heart Association in America.
لقد بدأنا بمبادرة سُمنة الأطفال مع جمعية القلب في أمريكا.
We tried to do the same thing by negotiating industry-right deals
حاولنا فعل نفس الشئ بالتفاوض حول إتفاقات حقوق التصنيع
with the soft drink and the snack food industry to cut the caloric
مع قطاع سوق المشروبات والوجبات الخفيفة لتقليل السعرات الحرارية
and other dangerous content of food going to our children in the schools.
وبعض المحتويات الأخرى الخطيرة للغذاء الذي يتناوله أطفالنا في المدارس.
We just reorganized the markets.
لقد تعرفنا للتو على الأسواق.
And it occurred to me that in this whole non-governmental world,
ولقد وضح لي أنه في العالم الغير حكومي هذا،
somebody needs to be thinking about organizing public goods markets.
يحتاج الشخص ليفكر حول تنظيم أسواق السلع العامة.
And that is now what we're trying to do,
وذلك ما نحاول القيام به الآن،
and working with this large cities group to fight climate change,
ونعمل مع مجموعات المدن الضخمة هذه لمكافحة تغير المناخ
to negotiate huge, big, volume deals that will enable cities
للتفاوض على إتفاقات ضخمة، كبيرة الحجم التي ستمكّن المدن
which generate 75 percent of the world's greenhouse gases,
التي تنتج 75 في المائة من غازات الدفيئة عالمياً
to drastically and quickly reduce greenhouse gas emissions
للتقليل الجذري والعاجل من إنبعاثات غازات الدفيئة
in a way that is good economics.
بطريقة جيدة للإقتصاد.
And this whole discussion as if it's some sort of economic burden,
وكل هذا النقاش كما لو أنه نوع من العبء الإقتصادي،
is a mystery to me.
هو لغز بالنسبة لي.
I think it's a bird's nest on the ground.
أعتقد أنه عش طائر على الأرض.
When Al Gore won his well-deserved Oscar
عندما فاز آل غور بجدارة بالأوسكار
for the "Inconvenient Truth" movie, I was thrilled,
عن فيلم الحقيقة المزعجة، شعرت بالغبطة،
but I had urged him to make a second movie quickly.
لكني قمت بحثه على عمل فيلم آخر بسرعة.
For those of you who saw "An Inconvenient Truth,"
لأؤلئك الذين شاهدوا "الحقيقة المزعجة،"
the most important slide in the Gore lecture is the last one,
أهم شريحة في حديث آل غور هي آخر شريحة،
which shows here's where greenhouse gases are going
التي تعرض إلى أين تتجه غازات الدفيئة
if we don't do anything, here's where they could go.
إذا لم نفعل شيئاً، ها هنا حيث سنذهب.
And then there are six different categories
ثم هناك ست فئات مختلفة
of things we can do to change the trajectory.
لأشياء يمكن أن نفعلها لتغيير هذه المأساة.
We need a movie on those six categories.
نحتاج لأفلام لتلك الفئات.
And all of you need to have it embedded in your brains
ويحتاج كلكم لأن يخزنها في عقله
and to organize yourselves around it.
ولتنظيم أنفسنا حولها.
So we're trying to do that.
إذاً نحن نحاول فعل ذلك.
So organizing these markets is one thing we try to do.
لذا فتنظيم هذه الأسواق هي شئ نحاول القيام به.
Now we have taken on a second thing, and this gets to my wish.
الآن لقد أخذنا ثاني شئ، وهذا يصلني لأمنيتي.
It has been my experience in working in developing countries
لقد كانت خبرتي في العمل في الدول النامية
that while the headlines may all be -- the pessimistic headlines may say,
بينما كانت عناوين الاخبار ربما كلها-- عناوين الأخبار المتشائمة إذا جاز لي القول،
well, we can't do this, that or the other thing because of corruption --
حسناً، لا نستطيع فعل هذا أو شئ آخر بسبب الفساد،
I think incapacity is a far bigger problem in poor countries than corruption,
أعتقد أن العجز هو أكبر بكثير من المشكلة في الدول الفقير عن الفساد،
and feeds corruption.
ويغذي الفساد.
We now have the money, given these low prices, to distribute
نحن الآن لدينا المال، بإعتبار تلك الأسعار المنخفضة، لتوزيع
AIDS drugs all over the world to people we cannot presently reach.
عقاقير الإيدز متوفرة في كل العالم لإناس ليس بمقدورنا الوصول اليهم حالياً.
Today these low prices are available in the 25 countries where we work,
اليوم هذه الأسعار المنخفضة متاحة في 25 دولة حيث نعمل،
and in a total of 62 countries,
وفي المجموع ل 62 دولة.
and about 550,000 people are getting the benefits of them.
ويحصل حوالي 550 ألف شخص على فائدتها.
But the money is there to reach others.
لكن المال هناك ليصل لآخرين.
The systems are not there to reach the people.
الأنظمة ليست هناك لتصل الى الناس.
So what we have been trying to do,
لذا ما كنا نحاول القيام به،
working first in Rwanda and then in Malawi and other places --
العمل في رواندا وملاوي وأماكن أخرى--
but I want to talk about Rwanda tonight --
لكني أرغب في التحدث عن رواندا الليلة--
is to develop a model for rural health care in a very poor area
هو تطوير نموذج للرعاية الصحية في الأماكن الفقيرة جداً في الريف
that can be used to deal with AIDS, TB, malaria, other infectious diseases,
يمكن إستخدامه للتعامل مع الإيدز، السُل، الملاريا، والأمراض المعدية الأخرى،
maternal and child health, and a whole range of health issues
صحة الأم والطفل، ومجموعة كاملة من القضايا الصحية
poor people are grappling with in the developing world,
للفقراء الذين يتصارعون في الدول النامية،
that can first be scaled for the whole nation of Rwanda,
الذي يمكن تحجيمه في البداية على كل الأمة في رواندا،
and then will be a model that could literally
ثم يكون نموذجاً يمكن حرفياً
be implemented in any other poor country in the world.
تطبيقه في أي دول فقيرة أخرى في العالم.
And the test is: one, will it do the job?
والإختبار هو: واحد، هل ستفي بالغرض،
Will it provide high quality care?
هل سيتطور-- يقدم رعاية عالية الجودة؟
And two, will it do it at a price
واثنان، هل سينجح بالسعر
that will enable the country to sustain a health care system
الذي سيمكّن البلاد من إستدامة نظام رعاية صحية
without foreign donors after five to 10 years?
بدون المساعدات الأجنبية بعد خمس الى 10 سنوات؟
Because the longer I deal with these problems,
لأنه كلما طال أمد التعامل مع هذه المشاكل،
the more convinced I am that we have to --
كلما أكون مرتاحاً بما ينبغي علينا --
whether it's economics, health, education, whatever --
سواء إقتصادياً، صحياً، التعليم، أي شئ--
we have to build systems.
ينبغي علينا بناء الأنظمة.
And the absence of systems that function
وغياب الأنظمة الفاعلة
break the connection which got you all in this seat tonight.
يكسر الرابط الذي أتى بكم جميعاً لهذه المقاعد الليلة.
You think about whatever your life has been,
مهما كان رأيك في حياتك الماضية،
however many obstacles you have faced in your life,
لكن هناك العديد من الصعاب التي واجهتموها خلال حياتكم،
at critical junctures you always knew
في المراحل الحاسمة كنتم دائماً تعلمون
there was a predictable connection between the effort you exerted
أن هناك رابط متوقع بين الجهود التي بذلتموها
and the result you achieved.
والنتائج التي حققتموها.
In a world with no systems, with chaos,
في عالم بدون أنظمة، مع الفوضى،
everything becomes a guerilla struggle,
كل شئ يصبح كفاح حرب العصابات،
and this predictability is not there.
والتوقع غير موجود.
And it becomes almost impossible to save lives,
ويصبح شبه مستحيل إنقاذ الأرواح،
educate kids, develop economies, whatever.
تعليم الأطفال، تنمية الإقتصاد، أي شئ.
The person, in my view,
الشخص، في نظري،
who has done the best job of this in the health care area,
الذي أنجز أفضل عمل في قطاع الرعاية الصحية هذا،
of building a system in a very poor area, is Dr. Paul Farmer,
في بناء الأنظمة في المناطق الفقيرة جداً هو د.باول فارمر،
who, many of you know, has worked for now 20 years with his group,
الذي يعرفه الكثير منكم، الذي عمل الآن 20 سنة مع مجموعته،
Partners in Health, primarily in Haiti where he started,
شركاء في الصحة، في الأساس في هاييتي حيث بدأ.
but they've also worked in Russia, in Peru
لكنهم كذلك عملوا في روسيا، في بيرو
and other places around the world.
وأماكن أخرى حول العالم.
As poor as Haiti is, in the area where Farmer's clinic is active --
بفقر هاييتي، في المنطقة التي تعمل فيها عيادة المزارعين --
and they serve a catchment area far greater
وهم يخدمون منطقة تجمّع أكبر بكثير
than the medical professionals they have would indicate they could serve --
من الأطباء المهنيين لديهم ما يشير الى أنهم يمكن أن يخدموا--
since 1988, they have not lost one person to tuberculosis, not one.
منذ 1988، لم يفقدوا ولا شخص واحد بسبب السُل، ولا شخص.
And they've achieved a lot of other amazing health results.
ولقد حققوا الكثير من النتائج الطبية المذهلة الأخرى.
So when we decided to work in Rwanda
لذا فعندما قررنا العمل في رواندا
on trying to dramatically increase the income of the country and fight the AIDS problem,
في محاولة زيادة كبيرة في دخل البلاد ونحارب مشاكل الإيدز،
we wanted to build a healthcare network,
أردنا بناء شبكة رعاية صحية،
because it had been totally destroyed during the genocide in 1994,
لأنها كانت مدمرة كلياً خلال الإبادة الجماعية عام 1994،
and the per capita income was still under a dollar a day.
ودخل الفرد كان ما يزال أقل من دولار يومياً.
So I rang up, asked Paul Farmer if he would help.
لذا فقد أتصلت ببول فارمر وطلبت مساعدته.
Because it seemed to me if we could prove there was a model in Haiti
لأنه بدى لي بأننا إن لم نستطيع إثبات أن هناك نموذج في هاييتي
and a model in Rwanda that we could then take all over the country,
ونموذج في رواندا يمكن أن نأخذه لكل البلدان،
number one, it would be a wonderful thing for a country
أولاً، سيكون شيئاً رائعاً للبلد
that has suffered as much as any on Earth in the last 15 years,
التي عانت بشدة أكثر من اي مكان آخر في ال 15 سنة الأخيرة،
and number two, we would have something that could then be adapted
وثانياً، سنحصل على شئ يمكن بعد ذلك تكييفه
to any other poor country anywhere in the world.
مع أي دولة فقيرة في أي مكان في العالم.
And so we have set about doing that.
ولذا قررنا فعل ذلك.
Now, we started working together 18 months ago.
الآن، بدأنا العمل سوياً قبل 18 شهر مضت.
And we're working in an area called Southern Kayonza,
ونعمل في منطقة تسمى جنوب كايونزا،
which is one of the poorest areas in Rwanda,
التي هي أحد أفقر المناطق في رواندا،
with a group that originally includes about 400,000 people.
مجموعة في الأصل تشمل حوالي 400 ألف شخص.
We're essentially implementing what Paul Farmer did in Haiti:
نحن نقوم في الأساس بتطبيق ما فعله باول فارمار في هاييتي،
he develops and trains paid community health workers
حيث يطوّر ويدرب موظفي صحة مدفوعي الأجر
who are able to identify health problems,
الذين بمقدورهم التعرف على المشاكل الصحية،
ensure that people who have AIDS or TB are properly diagnosed
والتأكد من أن المصابين بالإيدز أو السُل يتم تشخصيهم بصورة صحيحة
and take their medicine regularly,
ويأخذون عقاقيرهم بصورة راتبة،
who work on bringing about health education, clean water and sanitation,
الذين يعملون في تقديم تعليم صحي، مياة نظيفة وصرف صحي،
providing nutritional supplements and moving people up the chain of health care
يقدمون إمدادات غذائية وينتقلون بالناس عبر سلسلة الرعاية الصحية
if they have problems of the severity that require it.
إذا كان لديهم مشاكل للشدة التي تتطلب ذلك.
The procedures that make this work have been perfected,
الإجراءات التي جعلت هذا العمل مصقول،
as I said, by Paul Farmer and his team
كما قلت، كانت من باول فارمر وفريقه
in their work in rural Haiti over the last 20 years.
في عملهم في ريف هاييتي خلال ال 20 سنة الماضية.
Recently we did an evaluation of the first 18 months of our efforts in Rwanda.
مؤخراً قمنا بعمل تقييم لأول 18 شهر من جهودنا في رواندا.
And the results were so good that the Rwandan government
وكانت النتائج جيدة للغاية بحيث وافقت الحكومة الرواندية
has now agreed to adopt the model for the entire country,
الآن على تبني النموذج لكل البلاد،
and has strongly supported and put the full resources of the government behind it.
ودعمته بشدة ووضعت كل موارد الحكومة خلفه.
I'll tell you a little bit about our team because it's indicative of what we do.
سأخبركم قليلاً حول فريقنا لأنه يدل على ما نفعله.
We have about 500 people around the world
لدينا حوالي 500 شخص حول العالم
working in our AIDS program, some of them for nothing --
يعملون في برامجنا للإيدز، بعضهم بدون أجر--
just for transportation, room and board.
فقط المواصلات، المسكن والملبس.
And then we have others working in these other related programs.
ثم لدينا آخرين يعملون في برامج أخرى ذات صلة.
Our business plan in Rwanda
خطتنا في رواندا
was put together under the leadership of Diana Noble,
وُضعت معاً تحت قيادة ديانا نوبل،
who is an unusually gifted woman,
التي هي إمرأة موهوبة غير عادية ،
but not unusual in the type of people who have been willing to do this kind of work.
لكنها ليست النوع غير العادي من الناس الذين يرغبون في فعل هذا النوع من العمل.
She was the youngest partner at Schroder Ventures in London in her 20s.
لقد كانت أصغر شريك في مشاريع شرودر في لندن في عشريناتها.
She was CEO of a successful e-venture --
وكانت المدير التنفيذي لمشروع e-venture الناجح--
she started and built Reed Elsevier Ventures --
لقد أسست وبنت شركات ريد إلسيفر--
and at 45 she decided she wanted to do something different with her life.
وفي عمر 45 أرادت فعل شئ مختلف في حياتها.
So she now works full-time on this for very little pay.
لذا فهي تعمل الآن بدوام كامل على هذا الأجر الصغير جداً.
She and her team of former business people have created a business plan
إنها وفريقها من رجال الأعمال السابقين وضعوا خطة عمل
that will enable us to scale this health system up for the whole country.
ستمكننا من تحجيم نظام الرعاية الصحية هذا لكل البلد.
And it would be worthy of the kind of private equity work
وسيكون جديرا هذا النوع من عمل الأسهم الخاصة
she used to do when she was making a lot more money for it.
لقد أستخدمته عندما كانت تدّر الكثير من المال مقابله.
When we came to this rural area, 45 percent of the children under the age of five
عندما نأتي لهذه المنطقة الريفية، 45 في المائة من الأطفال تحت سن الخامسة
had stunted growth due to malnutrition.
توقف نموهم بسبب سوء التغذية.
23 percent of them died before they reached the age of five.
23 في المائة منهم مات قبل أن يصل سن الخامسة.
Mortality at birth was over two-and-a-half percent.
معدل الوفيات عند الولادة أكثر من أثنين ونصف في المائة.
Over 15 percent of the deaths among adults and children occurred
أكثر من 15 في المائة من الوفيات بين البالغين والأطفال حدث
because of intestinal parasites and diarrhea from dirty water and inadequate sanitation --
بسبب الطفيليات المعوية والاسهال من المياه القذرة وعدم كفاية المرافق الصحية،
all entirely preventable and treatable.
وكلها يمكن الوقاية منها وعلاجها تماماً.
Over 13 percent of the deaths were from respiratory illnesses --
أكثر من 13 في المائة من الوفيات الأخرى ناجمة عن أمراض الجهاز التنفسي--
again, all preventable and treatable.
مجدداً، جميعها يمكن الوقاية منها وعلاجها.
And not a single soul in this area was being treated for AIDS or tuberculosis.
ولا توجد ولا روح واحدة في المنطقة تم علاجها من الإيدز أو السُل.
Within the first 18 months, the following things happened:
خلال أول 18 شهر، حدثت هذه الاشياء:
we went from zero to about 2,000 people being treated for AIDS.
ذهبنا من صفر لحوالي ألفين شخص يتم علاجهم من الإيدز.
That's 80 percent of the people who need treatment in this area.
ذلك 80 في المائة من الناس الذين يحتاجون علاجاً في هذه المنطقة.
Listen to this: less than four-tenths of one percent of those being treated
أسمعوا هذا: أقل من أربع أعشار واحد في المائة من الذين يتم علاجهم
stopped taking their medicine or otherwise defaulted on treatment.
توقفوا عن تناول الدواء أو غير ذلك من ترك العلاج.
That's lower than the figure in the United States.
ذلك أقل من الرقم الموجود في الولايات المتحدة.
Less than three-tenths of one percent
أقل من ثلاث أعشار من واحد في المائة
had to transfer to the more expensive second-line drugs.
توجب عليهم الإنتقال لعلاج الخط الثاني الأكثر غلاءً.
400,000 pregnant women were brought into counseling
400 ألف إمرأة حامل حضرن للإستشارة
and will give birth for the first time within an organized healthcare system.
وسينجبن لأول مرة بوجود نظام رعاية صحية منظم.
That's about 43 percent of all the pregnancies.
ذلك حوالي 43 في المائة من كل الحوامل.
About 40 percent of all the people -- I said 400,000. I meant 40,000.
حوالي 40 في المائة من كل الناس-- قلت 400 ألف، أعني 40 ألفاً.
About 40 percent of all the people who need TB treatment are now getting it --
حوالي 40 في المائة من الناس الذين أحتاجوا علاج السُل الآن يحصلون عليه--
in just 18 months, up from zero when we started.
في 18 شهراً فقط، إرتفاع من صفر عندما بدأنا.
43 percent of the children in need of an infant feeding program
43 في المائة من الأطفال المحتاجين لبرامج تغذية الرُضع
to prevent malnutrition and early death
لمنع سوء التغذية والوفيات المبكرة
are now getting the food supplements they need to stay alive and to grow.
الآن يحصلون على الإمدادات الغذائية التي يحتاجون للبقاء على قيد الحياة والنمو.
We've started the first malaria treatment programs they've ever had there.
لقد بدأنا أول برنامج لعلاج الملاريا يتم هناك على الإطلاق.
Patients admitted to a hospital that was destroyed during the genocide
دخل المرضى للمستشفى الذي تم تدميره خلال الإبادة الجماعية
that we have renovated along with four other clinics,
وقمنا بإعادة تجديده بجانب أربع عيادات أخرى،
complete with solar power generators, good lab technology.
كاملة مع مولدات كهرباء تعمل بالطاقة الشمسية، ومعدات مختبر بتكنلوجيا جيدة.
We now are treating 325 people a month,
نحن الآن نعالج 325 شخص شهرياً،
despite the fact that almost 100 percent of the AIDS patients are now treated at home.
رغماً عن حقيقة أن 100 في المائة تقريباً من مرضى الإيدز الآن يتعالجون في البيت.
And the most important thing is
والشئ الأهم هو
because we've implemented Paul Farmer's model, using community health workers,
لأننا قمنا بتطبيق نموذج باول فارمر، بإستخدام عمال الصحة من المجتمع
we estimate that this system could be put into place for all of Rwanda
نقدر أن هذا النظام يمكن تطبيقه في كل رواندا
for between five and six percent of GDP,
مقابل ما بين خمسة لستة في المائة من الناتج الإجمالي المحلي(GDP)،
and that the government could sustain that
ويمكن للحكومة إستدامة ذلك
without depending on foreign aid after five or six years.
بدون الإعتماد على المساعدات الأجنبية بعد خمسة أو ست سنوات.
And for those of you who understand healthcare economics
ولأؤلئك منكم الذين يفهمون إقتصاديات الرعاية الصحية
you know that all wealthy countries spend between nine and 11 percent of GDP
تعرفون أن البلدان الغنية تنفق بين تسعة و11 في المائة من ناتجها المحلي الإجمالي
on health care, except for the United States, we spend 16 --
على الرعاية الصحية، بإستثناء الولايات المتحدة، نحن ننفق 16 --
but that's a story for another day.
لكن هذه قصة ليوم آخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We're now working with Partners in Health and the Ministry of Health in Rwanda
نحن نعمل الآن مع شركاء في الصحة ووزارة الصحة في رواندا
and our Foundation folks to scale this system up.
وجمهور منظمتنا لتحجيم هذا النظام.
We're also beginning to do this in Malawi and Lesotho.
نحن أيضاً نبدأ في فعل هذا في ملاوي وليسوثو.
And we have similar projects in Tanzania, Mozambique,
ولدينا مشاريع مشابهة في تنزانيا، موزمبيق،
Kenya and Ethiopia with other partners trying to achieve the same thing:
كينيا واثيوبيا وشركاء آخرين يحاولون تحقيق نفس الشئ،
to save as many lives as quickly as we can,
لإنقاذ أكثر أرواح بأقصى سرعة نستطيعها،
but to do it in a systematic way that can be implemented nationwide
لكن لفعل ذلك بطريقة سلسلة يمكن تطبيقها على كل البلد
and then with a model that can be implemented in any country in the world.
ثم مع نموذج يمكن تطبيقه في أي بلد في العالم.
We need initial upfront investment to train doctors, nurses,
نحتاج لإستثمار مبدئي مقدماً لتدريب الأطباء، الممرضات،
health administration and community health workers throughout the country,
الإدارات الطبية وموظفي الصحة في المجتمع عبر البلاد،
to set up the information technology, the solar energy,
لإقامة تقنية معلومات، طاقة شمسية،
the water and sanitation, the transportation infrastructure.
المياة والصرف الصحي، البنية التحتية للمواصلات.
But over a five- to 10-year period,
ولكن على مدى خمس إلى 10 سنوات،
we will take down the need for outside assistance
سنقلل الحوجة للمساعدات الخارجية
and eventually it will be phased out.
وفي نهاية المطاف سيتم الاستغناء عنها تدريجيا.
My wish is that TED assist us in our work and help us to build
أمنيتي تيد خاصتي هي مساعدتنا في عملنا لبناء
a high-quality rural health system in a poor country, Rwanda,
نظام رعاية صحية عالي الجودة في الدول الفقيرة، رواندا،
that can be a model for Africa,
يمكن أن تكون نموذجاً لأفريقيا،
and indeed, for any poor country anywhere in the world.
وبالطبع، لأي دولة فقيرة في أي مكان في العالم.
My belief is that this will help us to build a more integrated world
إعتقادي أن هذا سيساعدنا في بناء عالم أكثر تكاملاً
with more partners and fewer terrorists,
مع شركاء أكثر وإرهابيين أقل،
with more productive citizens and fewer haters,
ومع مواطنين منتجين أكثر وأقل كراهيةً،
a place we'd all want our kids and our grandchildren to grow up in.
مكان نرغب جميعنا أن يترعرع فيه أطفالنا وأحفادنا .
It has been an honor for me, particularly, to work in Rwanda
لقد كان شرفاً لي، تحديداً أن أعمل في رواندا
where we also have a major economic development project
حيث أيضاً لدينا مشاريع تنمية إقتصادية كبيرة
in partnership with Sir Tom Hunter, the Scottish philanthropist,
شراكة مع السير توم هنتر، الفيلسوف الاسكتلندي،
where last year we, using the same thing with AIDS drugs,
حيث قمنا في العام الماضي بإستخدام نفس الشئ مع عقاقير الإيدز،
cut the cost of fertilizer and the interest rates on microcredit loans by 30 percent
بتقليل قيمة الأسمدة ومعدل الفائدة على القروض الصغيرة ب 30 في المائة
and achieved three- to four-hundred percent increases
وحققنا زيادة بثلاثمائة الى أربعمائة في المائة
in crop yields with the farmers.
في حصاد المزارعين.
These people have been through a lot and none of us, most of all me,
هؤلاء الناس مروا بالكثير ولا أحد منا، وأكثرهم أنا،
helped them when they were on the verge of destroying each other.
ساعدهم عندما كانوا على وشك تدمير بعضهم البعض.
We're undoing that now, and they are so over it and so into their future.
نحن الآن نتراجع عن ذلك، ولقد تخطوا ذلك من أجل مستقبلهم.
We're doing this in an environmentally responsible way.
نحن نفعل هذا بطريقة مسؤولة بيئيا.
I'm doing my best to convince them not to run the electric grid
أبذل قصارى جهدي لإقناعهم بتشغيل شبكة الكهرباء
to the 35 percent of the people that have no access,
لل 35 في المائة من الناس الذين ليس لديهم كهرباء،
but to do it with clean energy. To have responsible reforestation projects,
لكن ليفعلوها بطاقة نظيفة، لإقامة مشاريع التشجير المسؤولة.
the Rwandans, interestingly enough, have been quite good, Mr. Wilson,
الروانديون، من المثير للاهتمام كانوا جيدين للغاية، السيد ويلسون
in preserving their topsoil.
في الحفاظ على تربتهم السطحية.
There's a couple of guys from southern farming families --
هناك عدة أشخاص من أسر الجنوب الزراعية--
the first thing I did when I went out to this place
أول شئ فعلته عندما ذهبت لهذا المكان
was to get down on my hands and knees and dig in the dirt
كان أن أنكببت على يدي وركبتي وحفرت التراب
and see what they'd done with it.
لرؤية ما فعلوه به.
We have a chance here to prove that a country
لدينا فرصة هنا لإثبات أن هذا البلد
that almost slaughtered itself out of existence
الذي كاد أن يمحي نفسه من الوجود
can practice reconciliation, reorganize itself, focus on tomorrow
يمكن أن يمارس المصالحة، ويعيد تنظيم نفسه، بالتركيز على غداً
and provide comprehensive, quality health care with minimal outside help.
وتقديم رعاية صحية شاملة وذات جودة عالية مع أقل مساعدة خارجية.
I am grateful for this prize, and I will use it to that end.
أنا سعيد بهذه الجائزة، وسأستخدمها لذلك الغرض.
We could use some more help to do this,
يمكننا الإستعانة بمزيد من المساعدة لفعل هذا،
but think of what it would mean if we could have a world-class health system
لكن فكروا في ماذا سيعني إذا أستطعنا الحصول على نظام رعاية صحية بمستوى عالمي
in Rwanda -- in a country with a less-than-one-dollar-a-day-per-capita income,
في رواندا -- في البلد الذي فيه معدل دخل الفرد أقل من دولار يومياً،
one that could save hundreds of millions of lives
نظام يمكن أن ينقذ مئات الملايين من الأرواح
over the next decade if applied to every similarly situated country on Earth.
خلال العقد القادم إذا تم تطبيقه في كل دولة مشابهة على الأرض.
It's worth a try and I believe it would succeed.
إنها تستحق المحاولة وأعتقد أنها ستنجح.
Thank you and God bless you.
شكراً لكم وبارك الله فيكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)